all right
[Music]
the human mouth is an important habitat
for microbes harboring up to 10 billion
bacteria and no wonder it's a warm and
moist providing a suitable environment
for bacterial growth some of which are
actually beneficial for example it's
widely recognized that dietary nitrate
affords cardiovascular protection by
turning into nitric oxide and guess what
contributes to the generation of nitric
oxide our oral microbiome first we
nitrate-rich vegetables like dark green
leafies and beets the nitrate is then
absorbed into our bloodstream and our
body then pulls it out of circulation to
be concentrated in our salivary glands
and secreted back into the oral cavity
why because our body knows there are
good bacteria on our tongue to tweak it
eventually resulting in the synthesis of
the artery protecting nitric oxide we've
got more than a billion people with high
blood pressure most of which is
uncontrolled as such as critical to
optimize daily behaviors to support
blood pressure regulation and
incorporating nitrate-rich Foods maybe
an optimal strategy as it supports
opening of arteries via the entero
salivary pathway the gut saliva pathway
thanks to the friendly Flora in our
mouth dietary nitrate can provide
sustained blood pressure lowering and
that starts with eating our greens leafy
green vegetables contribute 80 percent
of nitrate intake but it doesn't matter
how many greens we eat if we have oral
dysbiosis if we don't have the right
tongue bugs to take advantage of them
how can you screw up your oral friendly
Flora by using an antiseptic mouthwash
yeah it can kill the bad bugs that cause
plaque but it can indiscriminately kill
the good bugs too and that can have
systemic consequences for example
studies show an increase in blood
pressure following the use of
antibacterial mouth rinses because they
reduce the protective bacteria in your
mouth necessary for the nitric oxide
pathway a pathway that's vital to blood
pressure regulation and overall
cardiovascular health
just a single week of antibacterial
mouthwash use can cause a significant
increase in blood pressure it's not just
one city all human studies done to date
have revealed deleterious effects of
antibacterial mouthwash okay so what
about tongue cleaning brushing your
tongue or using a tongue scraper
regular tongue cleaning is recommended
by the American Dental Association as a
way to cut down on the bacteria on your
tongue that cause bad breath but if it
wipes out those bacteria it might Wipe
Out the good ones too it turns out
tongue cleaning may give you the best of
both worlds those who clean their tongue
twice or more per day as part of their
normal oral hygiene we're more likely to
have an increase in systolic blood
pressure during use of the antibacterial
mouthwash suggesting they had more of
the good bugs to kill here's the graph
the mouthwash was worse for those with
better tongue hygiene so regular tongue
cleaning may result in a baseline tongue
microbiome that has a greater ability to
tweak nitrate and conversely failure to
clean the tongue daily may result in the
microbiome composition that is
unfavorable to nitrate conversion number
wait a second maybe tongue cleaning just
disrupts the surface bacteria making
them easier for the mouthwash to pick
off to see if tongue cleaning was
actually associated with a better oil
microbiome they did DNA analyzes to
elucidate the Dynamics of the tongue
microbiome to compare differences
between time points and tongue hygiene
cohorts and it turns out tongue cleaning
does appear to have a significant impact
on the composition of the tongue
microbiome specifically increasing the
proportion of the good bacteria
So based on the study tongue cleaning
assumes a new importance from the
perspective of blood pressure regulation
as Daily Tongue cleaning appears to
favor The increased abundance and
metabolic activity the nitrate
metabolizing species like niceria
whereas failure to clean the tongue
daily may result in a microbiome
composition that is less favorable to
nitric oxide production now you still
have to eat your vegetables right
regular tongue cleaning together with
adequate dietary intake of nitrate since
that has a two-fold benefit first
dietary nitrate improves artery function
right eat some nitrate-rich vegetables
within three hours an improvement of
artery function and the nitrate can also
act as a Prebiotic for the oral
microbiome the most abundant best
nitrate converter is nyseria flavicans
and you can boost its abundance after
feeding it with vegetables after six
weeks of beet juice that's had its
nitrate removed not much change but
after six weeks of regular beaches and
niceria jumps right up making your mouth
a nitric oxide making machine
and if you look at the association
between nitrate reducing oral bacteria
and cardio metabolic outcomes having
more of this good bacteria in your mouth
is linked all sorts of cardio metabolic
benefits letting you take full advantage
of the veggies you eat
what if all you ate was plants the
impact of a vegan diet on the human
salivary microbiome and a fully
plant-based diet was Associated
significantly with more of the good nice
area bugs to help you churn out nitric
oxide so not only does eating
plant-based boost the beneficial
bacteria at the end of your digestive
tract but at the beginning too and
eating nitrate-rich vegetables like
greens doesn't just boost the good
bacteria but beats down the bad guys the
bacteria that cause cavities bad breath
and gum disease and indeed if you feed
people lettuce or lettuce juice so you
can do a randomized double blind
placebo-controlled trial with a lettuce
juice control that's had the nitrate
removed you can significantly improve
the health of your gums with greens the
researchers conclude that dietary
nitrate consumption may be a useful
adjunct to the control of chronic
gingivitis
so when reviews suggest there's no
reason to clean your tongue unless you
have bad breath and in the absence of a
coating on your tongue there's no reason
to clean it that was all before this new
data which suggests additional benefits
the only caveat would be those with
heart valve problems or a pacemaker or
anything else that puts you at risk for
endocarditis and infection within the
heart you may want to stay away from
tongue scraping given this case report
tentatively tying the two together just
like you can get a heart infection after
tongue piercing tongue scraping May
introduce a few bacteria into your
bloodstream that could be hazardous for
someone at risk
[Music]
thank you